And we had a pot. I mean, I'm not
exaggerating when I say they made a pot
of venison stew like this, and these
guys ate until they practically burst.
>> Oh my god, that's great.
I I didn't think I was going to be
skinning a deer tonight as part of work.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh, man.
Was that uh you And you said that was in
a rural part of the United States?
>> Yeah. Was it near Virginia? No. No.
>> No, it was out in the sticks.
So, one
could assume that maybe some training
operations were going on.
One could make that assumption.
>> [laughter]
>> You know what was so funny to me?
>> [snorts]
>> We had a break.
We had a break and it was part of it was
classroom instruction. So, we had a
break. So, I go into the men's room. A
whole bunch of guys went to the men's
room. It was all men.
And
it was one of the toilets, the urinals
were these ones that flushed themselves.
So, you know, you take a leak, you walk
away, it flushes itself, you wash your
hands.
The Jordanians are standing there,
they're all done.
And they're like pressing the pipe
and tapping the pipe and then they're
punching the pipe
cuz they couldn't figure out how to
flush it.
And they hadn't like
like they're still hanging out. They're
just standing there with their things
hanging out, like trying to
And I'm trying to explain to them
you can walk away. It It flushes itself.
They just couldn't And then finally the
the one who was the colonel, he's like,
"You Americans, you're so advanced.
How do you have these things? How does
it know that you're not there anymore?"
I said it's got a little thing in there.
I don't know. I don't know. I said we've
had these for a little while. It just
knows. It knows when you're when you're
all done. That's great. So, um
what's uh
not specific, you don't have to say a
specific intelligence agency, but is
there any like joint training that
stands out? Like what kind of stuff
would you guys do with other friendly
intelligence services?
>> It depends on the service cuz some are
really good at some stuff and really bad
at others. Um the first job that I had
that I came back where I when I came
back from Athens but before 9/11 was I
uh I was in an instructor in a group
that that trained intelligence services
around the world in counterterrorism
operations. So, because of my Arabic and
my field experience in the Middle East,
I handled all the Middle East.
But, that was specifically
counterterrorism operations, you know,
busting down doors or if you can't bust
down the door, you put a charge on the
door and blow it open and
we spent weeks weeks doing surveillance
and counter-surveillance.
So, everybody
I mean, just as a rule of thumb,
the CIA will work with with any country
that's friendly.
And even some that aren't friendly so
long as you have joint interests, you
know? I've always maintained, for
example,
that there are areas that we can work
with the Russians on right now, even in
a state of war.
Such as?
Counterterrorism, counternarcotics,
counterproliferation.
Definitely.
So, yeah, we started talking about
started talking about ground branch
um a little bit before.
So, I guess
just to kind of start start off there.
Like, what what is what has been your
experience with ground branch and
special activities and whatever they're
calling it now? Honestly, my experience
with all of those special activities uh
groups was
seeing them in the in the office and
saying, "Hope you had a good weekend."
Those guys, first of all,
almost none of them are career CIA
officers. They had long successful
careers in special forces of some sort,
the Navy SEALs, the Army Rangers, you
know, whatever.
Delta Force.
And at first, post-9/11, they were
seconded to the CIA for, you know, quick
strike operations.
And then as the years went by, the
agency decided to make many of them
official.
So, you put them under
global services or special activities
division or counterterrorism center.
And um
and they are actually
CIA employees. Others have retired from
the military and are at CIA as
contractors.
So, it's a much more efficient way of of
bringing them on board. But what they do
is so secret.
I mean that the nuts and bolts of it is
so secret that they just don't talk
about that stuff.
You know what they're doing, I know what
they're doing, everybody in the office
knows what they're doing.
Nobody mentions it. Mhm.
Can you explain like
what it is that they actually do to
people?
Yeah, the job is to
kill
or kidnap
uh and render
anybody who might be a threat to the
United States,
to an American citizen,
or to an American installation.
Now,
at the top of the food chain,
yeah, we we want those guys to be out
there killing the Osama bin Ladens and
the Ayman al-Zawahiris of the world. We
want them dead.
On the other hand,
you know, mistakes get made.
And
you've got people being snatched off the
street and rendered to third countries
and then tortured in those third
countries only then to have that
country's intelligence service come back
to the CIA and say, "Look, this is the
wrong guy."
And here you've been torturing him
mercilessly for the last 9 months, which
has happened repeatedly.
So, on the one hand, it's it's great.
Like, you know, who was it that said it
was it was Jose Rodriguez, the former
deputy director for operations, that you
need somebody who's willing to
um
who's willing to take these
tough decisions,
right? On the other hand,
as
as American government officials,
we live by the rule of law and by the
Constitution.
And so you also have to protect the
Constitution. And just going out there
wantonly murdering people and kidnapping
people and torturing people,
that's not upholding the Constitution.
So when I when I think about ground
branch or special activities division, I
think about, like you said, all those
retired special operations guys,
ex-Delta Force guys, ex-SEAL Team 6 guys
that basically go there to do the same
exact [__] that they were doing, Mhm.
you know, a special operations mission
set. Like, put like you said before, put
a charge on a door, blow it open, shoot
people in the face, and leave. But then
you hear about things like we'll get
into the Mossad, but that, you know,
they that one, it was Khaled Mashal, the
attempted
uh assassination in Jordan, Mhm. where
they sprayed him with poison. But like
so, my question is, at the CIA, is it
How is special activities structured? Do
they have like specialized units? There
are two different special activities
components.
One is its own division
within the CIA's Directorate of
Operations called the Special Activities
Division.
Before 9/11, that's that that were the
that was the only one,
right? And they would go do things in
the cover of darkness that nobody talked
about.
Then after 9/11,
the Counterterrorism Center
created its own special activities
group.
So these were guys that were on loan to
CTC
who would go out and specifically target
terrorists, people who were planning
operations against us.
I left before they could really figure
out who was going to do what over the
long term. So, I don't know how it's
structured. I do know that both
organizations still exist. And a lot of
what
the special activities guys do in CTC is
not assassinations, it's kidnappings.
So,
you know, it's it's
parachuting in somewhere,
stealing a van,
and
snatching somebody off the street. And
then you meet
the helicopter at the at the
departure point and then just fly the
guy to wherever it is you're going to
fly him. It's very dangerous, very very
dangerous work. Cuz you're
you're not snatching people off the
street in Dubai or Abu Dhabi, for
example. You're snatching them off the
street in Benghazi or Khartoum or, you
know,
Karachi or something.
So, a lot of moving parts, very very
dangerous. And if CIA people are being
killed, we wouldn't even know it because
they get their star on the wall of honor
and there's no name attached to the
star.
So, we we don't really know what's going
on with these groups.
So, you said what um people were on loan
to CTC from special activities? No, from
the military.
>> Oh. Mhm. And would that be like um I
forget what it's called, the Omega
program? Do you have Do you
Does that ring a bell? Mhm. I think
[clears throat] that was uh
>> my time.
So, that was when the CIA worked with uh
JSOC components. So, I think it was I
think it was mainly SEAL Team Six. I
want to say it wasn't uh Delta Force,
but JSOC and the CIA worked together and
You know, I will tell you in CTC at the
time,
post-9/11,
picture picture this. It's a big
bullpen. Got 100 150 people all in
cubicles. So many people, I said this
before, that we had to name the aisles,
right? So, there's like Bin Laden
Boulevard. Seriously, Hezbollah Highway.
So, you could tell people, "Oh, I I I
sit at the intersection of whatever."
Um
and then around the perimeter of that
big bullpen are all the private offices.
You have the chief CTC, deputy chief for
ops, deputy chief for analysis, deputy
chief for military affairs, and then the
group chiefs, and
all the big muckety-mucks have their own
small private offices.
Once those guys on loan from, say, SEAL
Team Six
came to the office, they never
interacted with any of us.
I mean, not even so much as a good
morning.
And so, I mean, we we kind of knew what
these guys were there to do. We knew who
they were. They just appeared one day,
you know, in the weeks after 9/11, and
then they would vanish for a week at a
time or two weeks at a time, and then
come back whispering to each other and
not interacting with you. So, it was
pretty easy to figure out who they were
and what they were up to.
I want to talk to you about CTC
specifically, but
not related to CTC necessarily, was
there a point when you were at the
agency after 9/11 where you saw it
turning into a paramilitary
organization? The day after 9/11.
Seriously.
The day after 9/11, Cofer Black
an hour after the attacks began, Cofer
Black stood on a chair right outside of
his office
and
it was
dead silent.
There were hundreds of us.
Silence.
And he said, "Today we're at war
and we're all going to have to fight.
Not all of us are going to come home.
So, if you want to walk out now,
walk out and no one will think less of
you."
One woman walked out.
And then her branch went to
went to the deputy director for analysis
and said, "We don't have confidence in
her leadership." And so, she was
removed.
But, uh
I mean, everybody volunteered. It was
literally within 24 hours
that we began this transition into a
paramilitary force.
There was no more uh focus on
recruiting spies to steal secrets,
right?
It was just about
destroying Al-Qaeda.
Destroying it permanently.
And to tell you the truth,
among core Al-Qaeda,
that that core of Al-Qaeda that was
based in Afghanistan, they were
destroyed by Christmas. Right? The
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, um
uh years before I joined it, of course,
came out with a with a study that
probably should have been classified and
wasn't. And they said that by the end of
2001, there were 25 active
Al-Qaeda members still in Afghanistan.
25.
It had been destroyed. And everybody
else who had made their way across the
border into Pakistan, we were capturing.
So, it was done. Now, of course, there
was
Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula, there
was Al-Qaeda in the Islamic Levant,
there was Al-Qaeda in North Africa.
Uh they were all in Al-Qaeda inspired,
but but weren't coordinating operations.
And and also, of course, we hadn't yet
killed either bin Laden or Zawahiri.
But in terms of Al-Qaeda as a fighting
force, it was done by Christmas of '01.
Did you Did you happen to see, um did
you happen to see the bin Laden
documentary?
Yeah, on Netflix? Yes. Dude, I
uh I I can't tell you how many people
reached out to me and were like, "Oh,
did you see Did you see this? Did you
see this?" And I was like, "No, I didn't
see it." And then I watched it, and it
was cool. It wasn't necessarily any new
information, except for one thing,
talking about CTC. I didn't know that uh
the cover quote, "The flies on eyeballs"
thing, was at Camp David,
and that's how he got the nod over
Rumsfeld and the DOD. That is I didn't
know that. That's a pretty cool story.
That is a cool story and everybody
picked it up at the time.
Cofer I always had deep respect for
Cofer. We can certainly have
disagreements on policy, but man, what a
patriot.
Um
Cofer meant
he was going to see flies on Bin Laden's
eyeballs when he was done.
And um
you know, you have to you have to
remember, too, that this was the
greatest intelligence failure in
American history. 3,000 Americans died
because we didn't do our jobs.
And so there was
a deep desire for revenge
after 9/11, which I understood fully.
And that's why, like everybody else in
the building, I kept volunteering over
and over to go to Afghanistan and do
whatever was required of me. Anything.
Anything.
And so in the end, you know, we all we
all had our roles. But Cofer
I was glad that Cofer
uh headed the effort rather than
Rumsfeld because if if Rumsfeld had
headed it,
it would have been a completely
different landscape in Afghanistan.
Yeah.
There's a couple things that are in my
head right now, but I have a feeling
people would really want me to ask you
about this. Did you Did you happen to
see Sean Ryan on Tucker? You did? Okay.
So, for people that maybe haven't, he he
talks about um
he interviewed this guy that was a CIA
and FBI agent that is an asset.
He Sean had him on his show.
And I didn't I didn't watch the full
episode, but just for context, let's say
this guy was um his story and his
credentials were, I don't know,
Al-Qaeda. Let's say that, right? And
let's say that he's Middle Eastern based
and that's where his story lives.
And at one point, he says something to
Sean about it was either the Russians
trying to proliferate nuclear material
or bring nuclear material somewhere and
it was something alarming related to
Russia.
And Shawn talks on Tucker about he's
like, well, I looked at the guy and I
asked him immediately I was like, when
is the last time that you had contact
with the agency?
And apparently this guy's story was that
he got burned by the agency. The agency
[__] him. That's what he claims. So he
says, well, no, it was, you know, when
they screwed me. That was the very last
time.
And Shawn goes, well, I'll tell you what
I'm thinking.
If the CIA found out that you were going
to come on this podcast, obviously the
Shawn Ryan Show has quite a bit of reach
and he's a uh
I think there's a difference between a
show having a lot of reach and the
show's host being reputable, which in my
opinion Shawn is. He's very reputable.
Um Yeah, he's the he's the real McCoy.
Yes. I'm dude, I modeled this whole show
off of him. I respect him a lot. I think
he's the goat. Anyway, um
he asked the guy, when's the last time
you had contact with the agency because
Good question. he seemed he felt like he
just threw that Russia thing in there.
And it was totally out of place. And the
theory would be like, if the agency
said, okay, you're going on this
podcast, say whatever you want, just
work in this one thing. And that got the
wheels turning in my head.
>> insightful. I just hadn't thought about
it that way. Like you would think there
people claim other
famous CIA officers are plants. I won't
say who.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh we don't need to go there, but just
that one nugget. Mhm. What do you think
about that?
I think that's a brilliant insight.
And I could absolutely see it.
100% absolutely see it. Yes.
Yes.
You know, people talk about
Operation Mockingbird and and the the
CIA's influence over the media.
They don't need to recruit
media figures anymore because the
American media just will gladly take
whatever the the CIA gives them and
they're they'll run with it. They'll
just gist a a CIA press release and call
it
call it news.
So, yeah, you know, a friend of mine
Jason Leopold. I don't know if you know
Jason. He's a He's an investigative
journalist with Bloomberg. He started
off at the LA Times. He went to Vice and
a couple of other different places. This
guy is absolutely brilliant. He's a
gifted writer.
He's a dogged investigator.
And breaks big stories. He's the one who
broke the Hillary Clinton email server
story. And the way he did it, the way he
does it every time
is he files these gigantic Freedom of
Information Act requests. Knowing that
the agency's never going to respond
within the 60 days or 90 days or
whatever it is. And so he sues them
every time. And he wins every time.
And so
he filed a Freedom of Information Act
request
asking for
all correspondence between the CIA's
Office of Public Affairs
and
all American journalists, period.
From this date to that date. And they
didn't respond and he sued and the judge
ruled in his favor and they had to just
turn over everything.
And he found
such interesting information.
He found
first
there was a um a reporter who wrote a
story that was a little bit anti-CIA.
And so the CIA emailed him and said,
"You better not publish this. If you
publish this, so help me God, you will
never be invited to the Christmas party
ever again and we will not comment on
any of your stories." And so he
withdrew.
They don't need to recruit the guy to
kill the story. They just threaten him.
Another thing that he found was Ken
Dilanian, who is the chief national
security correspondent at NBC News and
MSNBC.
He was writing articles about the
agency.
And then he was sending the articles to
the agency for clearance before he sent
them to his own editor.
That is absolutely unacceptable.
So, they don't need
to recruit anybody in the media. They
already own everybody in the media.
And if you're anti-agency and you're not
working for a well-funded media outlet,
uh you're screwed cuz you're just not
going to be able to get your message out
there.
That's why we're so fortunate to have
people like Matt Taibbi, for example,
who's able to get his message out thanks
to Substack.
You know, we need we need a thousand
Matt Taibbis, not these weaklings who
are just going to take whatever the CIA
gives them and just it and put their
name on the byline.
And then we find ourselves propagandized
by the agency.
I mean, that's the thing, man. Now that
I'm thinking about it, if you're an
independent podcaster and like me, I am
my team. I don't have a team. I don't
have a team of producers like Tucker to
try to verify That's right.
>> prior.
So, first of all, I would say the onus
is on people individuals that listen to
what they listen to to decide what they
want to believe. That needs to be number
one. Uh let me interrupt you on that
point cuz that's a very, very important
point that I hope everybody takes to
heart.
You can't trust anybody.
And so, you have to trust yourself.
And the only way you can trust yourself
is to consume everything.
You know, I get up in the morning,
people, friends of mine,
accuse me of being too mainstream. And
I'm actually not mainstream. But, you
have to know what the mainstream is
saying so that you can refute it. So, as
soon as I wake up in the morning, I read
the Washington Post, the New York Times,
the LA Times, the Wall Street Journal.
And then I go to CNN, Fox,
the Guardian, a couple of others. I read
the Greek papers just cuz I'm Greek and
I have an interest in it.
And then I go to the blogs and the
substacks and stuff like that. You have
to consume everything
and have confidence in your own
intellect. So, you can read something
and say, "Uh that's [__] That's
just not true."
And then you read something else, you
say, "That's plausible. That makes
sense. I'm going to watch that issue."
Because who you going to believe? You're
going to believe Ken Dilanian?
Right? I'm not.
You're going to believe the Washington
Post?
I like uh
Ellen Nakashima and Joby Warrick, but
then that's pretty much it.
There maybe are one or two people at the
New York Times. Nobody at the LA Times
anymore.
So, you you've got to be confident in
your own ability to discern what's true
or what's not true, or you just get
overwhelmed
with what is likely to turn out to be
propaganda. Yeah.
Yeah, dude. I mean, shoot. I don't I
don't know how to uh
you know, I think guest selection as a
podcast host is an important one. You
can't just platform anybody, but at the
same time
>> the truth? there's an argument to be
made that again, I think, you know, each
individual draws the line as you do, you
have a show. Um and you know, it's for
you or I to say where that line is, but
at the end of the day, you know,
information is out there. Make up your
mind on your own. Yeah, that's it. Like
like uh we talked about Scott Horton a
minute ago.
Um I've become something of a like a
semi-regular on the Piers Morgan uh
show.
And uh the last time I was on,
it was like a last-minute I think cuz
somebody dropped out. So, they said,
"Can you come on in 15 minutes?" I said,
"Sure."
So, I I log on and I see Scott and I was
like, "Oh, thank God, Scott's here.
Okay." So, this is going to be a serious
discussion.
Yeah. So, he wasn't scheduled to be Like
he's like a fill-in, you mean? Or Yeah,
he and I were both fill-ins, but as soon
as I saw Scott Horton, I thought, "Okay,
this is going to be a serious
intellectual conversation." Do you know
anything I think it was Scott that
mentioned this. Um
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> it might have been Scott or Darrell
Cooper, actually. I which Okay, I don't
I don't know what Darrell Cooper has
been canceled for, I'll say that. I I
listen to a lot of Tucker. I I like
Tucker's podcast.
>> Tucker a lot. It was one of those guys.
>> too. Yeah. Say what you want about
Tucker, I don't give a [__] I'm just
telling you I I listen to his podcast
sometimes and these two guys, one of
them said something about the National
Endowment for Democracy.
>> Mhm.
Do you know anything about that?
>> Huh?
I and I believe the context was that it
was a proxy for the CIA. Yeah, it is.
What does that mean?
The National Endowment for Democracy has
taken many millions of dollars from the
CIA to promote American propaganda.
Uh, mainstream American government
propaganda.
So, when it talks about things like
nation building, it's not really talking
about nation building. It's talking
about encouraging the development of
leaders in foreign countries that are
going to be knee-jerk supporters of the
US and US foreign policy.
So, it's mainly a
propaganda psyop sort of machine, for
lack of better term. It's not like
actual boots on the ground type
operations.
>> Not not at all boots on the ground.
>> Okay.
>> Not at all. No.
You know, when we liberated Kuwait in
1991,
I I've told you in the past, I went in
with the Marines on Liberation Day. It
was very, very exciting. One of the
highlights of my life, my adult life.
And then within days of Kuwait being
liberated, these Americans just kind of
show up.
And
they came to the embassy to register,
and then we would bump into each other
at events.
Remember, the country's literally on
fire. The Iraqis had blown up all the
oil wells, and there are these giant,
you know,
100-ft high flames gushing out of the
ground. It turned out these people were
from the Democratic National Committee
and the Republican National Committee.
I'm like, "What are you doing here?"
And they said, "Well, oh, we're here to
help them transition to democracy."
Well, it's a it's a monarchy. It's not
going to be They they have this little
elected, you know,
Majlis al-Watani, a national assembly,
but it's not going to ever be
democratic.
Well,
I was in my 20s then,
not really savvy enough to know that
this is all part of the plan. You use
the National Endowment for Democracy,
you use, you know, NPR, you use the DNC
and the RNC, and you all smile and get
along and go to cocktail parties, and
it's all just to promote American
propaganda. I I worked with a guy
briefly, John Rendon. God bless him.
Awesome guy.
And
I asked him one time, this is before he
hired me to do a contract, I asked him
what he did. He said, "Oh, I'm a
professional propagandist."
I said, "What does that mean?"
And he said, "Well, you were in Kuwait
on the liberation day?" And I said,
"Yeah." He said, "You remember when the
American tanks are rolling down the the
main street, the Corniche?" I said,
"Sure."
And he said, "And a million people are
out there waving little American flags?"
I said, "Yeah."
He said, "Where the hell do you think
those flags came from?"
The country's destroyed.
It's it's liberation day, but everybody
has American flag, and they're all
waving their little flags.
And I was like, "You know what? I never
even thought of it."
Mhm.
It's good living in propaganda.
What What was the contract that he asked
you to do? When was this? Oh.
>> [clears throat]
>> He hired me in 2008. I'm not I'm not I'm
not proud of this.
He hired me in 2008 to work with Karl
Rove, of all people.
Karl Rove, who had run the George W.
Bush campaigns, both of them,
to work on a presidential campaign in
Indonesia.
So, it was a guy named
General
Joko Widodo.
That was his name.
And
I was the good cop cuz I'm always the
good cop and Carl was the bad cop.
So we fly into Singapore and then we
helicopter over to uh
Jakarta. You can see Indonesia, it's
right across the water.
So this guy owns a chain of Holiday
Inns. He's a former chairman of the
Joint Chiefs of Staff of Indonesia.
And um
and Carl's like, "Yeah, you know, we can
do this and we can do that and we've got
TV commercials and radio commercials."
And I said, "Wait a minute. Wait a
minute. Wait a minute." I said, "General
with all due respect
there's video of you on YouTube
stabbing six peaceful protesters in the
heart.
How do we get past that?
You're You murdered six college students
because they participated in a peaceful
pro-democracy demonstration. I said,
"You're banned from the United States
for human rights reasons.
We can't just pretend it didn't happen."
And so I know, right? So the job was um
that I was going to write these op-eds
saying, "Oh, he's misunderstood." And so
I wrote these op-eds, no one would
publish them. You did this. I had So he
paid me to do it. He paid me very
handsomely.
So I wrote these op-eds, we sent them to
like the Wall Street Journal
the LA Times
the New York Times and people were like,
"Ooh,
no, we're not touching this." So nothing
ever came of it. He ended up He was
running for president. And we we needed
to rehabilitate his reputation. He said,
"Murderer."
And um
in the end he dropped out of the race
and got himself elected vice president.
But the ban the the American ban on his
travel was never lifted. He was never
welcomed in the United States again.
Yeah, he lined these guys up. It was six
college students. He li- He lined them
up and one by one stabbed each of them
in the heart.
Yeah.
Not good.
I
I guess they didn't have a a plethora of
wonderful candidates if
that was the guy that they wanted to
choose.
>> Indonesia is a tough gig, and it has a
lot of people. Good god, man. Yeah.
Well, I respect the fact that you shared
that. And to to our point about
nonsense, you know, if you were sticking
to a narrative, then you probably
wouldn't have. So, I appreciate that you
did, and that speaks to me
>> I'm not proud of it, but I had just
blown the whistle on the torture
program. I lost my job. I had five kids
or I had four kids at the time, and I
really, really needed an income.
And so, this opportunity comes, you
know, "Hey, would you take 25 grand to
write four op-eds?" And I said, "Yes,
definitely."
Um going back to Tucker again, when you
were on Tucker, I think it was, you
mentioned that there is agency
psychologists that you can take with you
on ops.
>> Mhm.
To again, going back to what we're
talking about before, find that crack
and make it wider. Yes.
>> What Like what would they help you with?
I have to tell you, the the one
operation that I did with a with an
agency psychologist was the most fun I
have ever had in a single operation.
We had a walk-in.
We had a walk A walk-in is somebody who
literally walks in to an
to an American embassy off the street
and says, "I have intelligence I want to
pass to the CIA."
95% of them are lunatics.
The The other 5% are intelligence
peddlers who just want you to give them
a couple of hundred dollars, and then
they go to the British embassy, and the
Russian embassy, and the French embassy,
and the Israeli embassy, and they just
do the same thing, and then that's a
month's salary, right?
Um some are uh
probes
from terrorist groups or enemy
countries. They're just looking to see
where the cameras are, how thick the
doors are, who's armed or not armed, how
far into the embassy they can get before
they're stopped.
But most of them are just lunatics.
And then there's 1% that's the real
deal.
If you look historically
by reading Cold War era memoirs, the
best recruits the CIA has ever had were
walk-ins. Because you don't know who
this Russian KGB colonel is, you're
never going to encounter him.
But then one day he just walks into an
embassy somewhere and says, "I'm a KGB
colonel and I want to give you
everything I have. And I want a million
dollars." And you say, "I'll get the
giant sack of money, you start writing,
you know."
I'm being facetious, of course, but not
too much. So,
we had a walk-in
who said that he had seen an
assassination.
He He said that
he's driving down this highway and he
has to take a leak.
And so he pulls off an exit and there's
this old abandoned church there and he
parks his car behind this big banyan
tree and he takes he's taking a leak.
And while he's taking a leak,
a van pulls up.
A bunch of guys get out of the back of
the van.
The source sees two motorcycles in the
back of the van and hears one of the
guys say,
"Does he still live?"
And the other one says, "He should be
dead by now."
So,
he says, "I think this was this
terrorist group that you guys are
after." And we said, "Will you sit with
a sketch artist?" He said, "Yes."
And he did the sketches and they were
really, really close to photographs we
had of people that we suspected were
in this terrorist group.
So,
we turned him over to the FBI.
And the FBI interviewed him and they
said, "He's full of [__] He's nuts.
We're done."
Well,
we just took him back.
And we said,
"How about if we fly to London?
We have a nice dinner.
Everybody's relaxed. We're all friends.
And we talk about this in more detail."
He said, "Great."
So, we fly him to London. He was so
poor, the poor guy. I remember this. He
flew to London. It was freezing.
And he didn't own a coat.
So, I went out and bought him a coat.
Uh just so he wouldn't, you know, be
frozen solid by the end of the
the three or four days.
So, I flew out to London with
two psychologists. But, one of the
psychologists was a licensed hypnotist.
And um
Uh and uh I flew out there with another
case officer.
So, we both spoke the language. And so,
we're going to act as translators for
the hypnotist.
It's hard work being a translator. And
let me tell you.
And you have to be like
speaking like this.
We're going to count backwards. 10
8. It's very hard.
So,
the night before,
we go out to some bookstore. We go to a
nice restaurant without the guy. The guy
hasn't arrived yet. So, just the agency
people. We went out. This is going to be
our plan. We're going to
you know, have all the lights off. We're
going to be in the darkened hotel room.
Speak very softly. We're going to put
him under. And I said, "Come on."
I said, "Hypnosis isn't really a thing,
right? It always just seemed like
[__] to me." And he said, "No, no,
no." He said, "We're going to We're
going to really put him under."
And he said, "You know, the funny thing
is that smart people go under much more
quickly than stupid people do."
Which I still don't fully understand.
But, he said we're going to we're going
to ask him all these questions. I said,
"Well, how long does this last?" He
said, "If If we get him under quickly,
we could do this for 2 and 1/2 or 3
hours." I'm like, "Okay, this is going
to be tough
being the translator.
So,
the guy arrives and you know, welcome.
This is Dr. So-and-so. This is the other
Dr. So-and-so. You know my colleague.
And so, you know, get comfortable.
You need a drink or you use the
bathroom. We're going to We're going to
hypnotize you to help you remember some
of the things that you saw that day.
So,
this is one of the wackiest things that
ever I ever witnessed at the agency.
So,
I was the first translator.
And I told him,
"We're going to count backwards from 10.
And just relax. And think about the
numbers, right?" So, we start. And he
said, "I want you to raise your hand
like this." And it wasn't propped. It
was up in the air like this.
And he said, "Don't put your hand down
until I tell you to."
He held his arm there
for 3 hours.
It was inhuman.
A conscious person couldn't do it.
So,
the guy is out before we get to zero
counting back from 10.
So,
I start asking him questions.
Okay, you pull off the exit.
You drive to the church. The church is
right off to the side of the road.
You go behind the banyan tree.
Then what are you doing? He said, "I'm
peeing."
And then what happens?
A van pulls up.
What does the van look like?
It's painted red. And it has some rust
spots over the the rear
wheels.
Then what do you see?
The back door's open. I see two
motorcycles and two men inside. I said,
"Can you see a license plate?" This
freaks me out. Oh, I got chills just
thinking about it. I said, "Can you see
a license plate?" He says, "Yes."
And he's he's like this with his eyes
closed. I said, "What does the license
plate say?" And he goes
And then he reads off the plate.
So, I write it down. I hand it to my
colleague. He goes into the other room
and he calls headquarters. He says, "We
need to run a plate ASAP."
So,
headquarters sends an immediate cable
out to the field. Call liaison. Run this
plate right now.
And the plate comes back stolen.
I couldn't [__] believe it.
I couldn't believe it.
And he's like this the whole time.
So, I said, "Are the men talking?" Yes.
"What are they saying?"
"Does he still live?"
"He should be dead by now."
"And then what happens?"
And he says, "They see me."
I said, "They see you?"
"Do they approach you?" He said, "Yes,
and one punches me in the face."
"And then what?" He said, "I'm bleeding
and I told them I didn't hear anything."
And he went on like this. It was this
long elaborate 3-hour long story.
So, I took notes like ridiculous, you
know, filled a notebook full of notes.
I called my boss at headquarters. I
said, "This is the craziest thing I've
ever seen." And my boss says, "I'm
freaking out over the stolen license
plate." He goes, "This may be the real
deal."
I I write all the notes. I go back to
station in London. I I write all the
notes and I send it back out into the
field.
And they're like, "Oh my god, the
details incredible. Okay, we're going to
try to get with him when he returns to
country."
So, a couple of weeks pass
and then he triggers a meeting.
And so, my colleague who I'd been with
in London,
flies out to meet with him. And the guy
says, "They know who I am.
They kidnapped me, and they took me to a
house,
and they beat me."
And we're like, "Okay,
where? Where was the house? When did
this happen? How many of them were
there? What did they look like? Were the
Were they the same guys you saw at the
church?"
He answered all these questions.
And I said to my colleague, I said,
"This doesn't make sense.
Because the only way they would know who
he was is if they were,
you know, with us.
We knew where he lived,
but
there's no way that they would know.
It just didn't make any sense."
So, I go to the FBI.
And it was There's this one agent.
She's actually big muckety-muck now in
the FBI, and she goes, "You CIA people,
you all have your heads up your asses,"
she said. And I said, "No, you FBI
people. I said, you think everybody's
lying to you. I said, we're going to get
medals when we crack this case." And she
goes, "Ah, you people." So, she wasn't
helpful to me.
Then he calls a second time, and he
says, um, that they kidnapped him again,
but he had a tape recorder on him,
and
the tape recorder was in his pocket, and
he recorded the whole encounter. We're
like, "Okay,
that's way too good to be true, but
let's listen to the tape."
So,
we play the tape, and he's like, it's
his voice, and he says,
"Hey,
>> [clears throat]
>> I know you. Don't hurt me." And then,
also his voice,
"I am the Minister of Public Order, and
I demand that you tell me about the CIA
people that you're meeting with." And I
was like, "Motherfucker.
You made the whole [__] thing up,
didn't you?
So, we decided to fly him back out to
London. Oh, let me finish the first part
first. So, he's got his arm like this.
And the hypnotist says,
"I'm going to count backwards to five
and then you're going to wake up."
And he goes, "Five, four, three, two,
one."
And he wakes up and his arm falls and he
looks around and he says, "What
happened?" And then he goes,
and then vomits all over himself.
So, he runs into the bathroom in the
hotel room to clean himself up. And the
hypnotist, who was like 110 years old,
he goes, "You know, I've read about this
in the literature, but I've never seen
it happen." I said, "I can't believe you
held his arm up like that for 3 hours."
It was nuts.
So, anyway, we fly him back out to
London.
We said, "No more [__]
You made this up." No, no, it was the
Minister of Public Order. He's with the
terrorists. We're like, "No, we we ran a
spectro- spectroscope on this. It's it's
you with your hand over your mouth to
try to make a different voice."
And he's like, "Oh, well, my wife has
cancer and I I was hoping that if you
believed me that you would pay for her
cancer treatment and I wanted her to go
to the Mayo Clinic." And we're like,
"Doesn't work that way."
And then the FBI just says, "I told you,
you [__] idiots. I told you in 3
months ago it was a lie."
So, I was like, "Yeah, okay. Well, you
win this one."
But the hypnosis part was actually that
was real?
>> That that He saw something at the church
that day. It probably wasn't the
terrorists.
But it was something untoward. It was
probably a bunch of guys that stole two
motorcycles.
That is spooky, dude. And like you hear
about um
>> [clears throat]
>> you hear the about the agency taking a
crack at like this remote viewing stuff?
>> Right. Since the 50s. Yeah. I
I've kind of
not looked into it, but like I've heard
a couple people talk about it in
interviews. Um
I don't really know what to make of it,
but as far as like spooky [__] like
that, like what what do you make of it?
It was kind of the craze in the 1950s,
you know, ESP and UFOs and astral
projection and moving items with your
mind and and the CIA had a an endless
budget. There was no such thing as an
oversight committee to say, "Hey, this
is a waste of the taxpayer's money."
And I'll tell you what really was the
was the motivator for the CIA is
is the Chinese
were successful in planting
disinformation in the CIA that the
Russians were developing the same
technology.
So, we were like, "Oh my god, we
recruited this Chinese intelligence guy
and he said the KGB's already doing it.
We have to catch up to The KGB wasn't
doing anything. They had never heard of
this stuff.
And then the Manchurian Candidate came
out and freaked everybody out in the
mid-50s.
So, the CIA spent millions and millions
of dollars experimenting with everything
from remote viewing to to
you know, UFOs and
all this crap just lumped into one
thing.
And nothing ever came of it. I mean,
that this is how MK Ultra was created.
Where okay, let's start with LSD.
There's this new thing called LSD that
this Swiss scientist accidentally
invented and you can see crazy [__] when
you take it and maybe we can microdose
it to make people do what we want them
to do like under hypnosis but without
them realizing that they're doing it.
And then we can double them back against
the KGB.
And then people are jumping out of hotel
windows and they're killing their
families, and losing their minds, and
and then as part of MK Ultra, there was
like MK Chickwit and MK
Seesaw, and there was a whole bunch of
them, like a half a dozen of them under
MK Ultra, where you know, we
we created a germ in a lab
and we just blew it into the atmosphere
in San Francisco just to see if anybody
would get sick.
And lots of people got sick.
11 of them were sick enough that they
happened to be uh to need
hospitalization.
And it turned out that they all suffered
from the same rare respiratory
infection. And the doctors are like,
[clears throat] "Where the heck did this
come from?"
Well, the CIA had it in a big tube, and
they were shooting it into the fog.
And they did it in San Francisco cuz the
fog is heavy, and they knew that the fog
would keep the germ close to the ground
where people are breathing it in.
And then the CIA said, "You know what we
should do?
We should hire a whole bunch of
prostitutes
and rent a rent a cathouse, a safehouse,
and we get these prostitutes to bring
Johns back to the back to the cathouse,
and then we dose them with LSD and see
if we can control their minds."
These are American citizens.
You can't just dose somebody with LSD.
It's "Ooh, let's see. Is he going to go
crazy? Is he going to kill himself? Is
he going to confess to, you know, his
deepest darkest secrets?" Like, what the
[__] wrong with people?
But we did that from 1952 to 1975.
And then in '75, when the Church
Committee
realized that this program had been
going on for more than two decades,
Senator Frank Church ordered the CIA,
"Do not destroy the documents."
And so they immediately destroyed the
documents.
There were about 20% of the documents
that had been misplaced and were found
later. So, what we know about MK Ultra
today is just from the 20% that
survived. Everything else was destroyed.
And then they were like, "Yeah, well,
they're destroyed. What are you going to
do about it?"
That's the insane part is it's such a
fraction of the available information,
and there's all of this stuff. And you
think about stuff like the psychic
driving stuff is so gnarly.
>> Right. Well, now
now
compare psychic driving with the
technologies that we have.
And you've created a monster. You know,
when the when the Vault 7 documents were
released
back in What was it? 2017?
What are those?
Um there was a CIA computer engineer who
named Joshua Schulte
who swears that he's innocent, but is
now serving a sentence of 40 years for
espionage. He was apparently allegedly a
disgruntled engineer. He didn't like his
boss. He didn't like his coworkers. They
didn't like him.
So, he just
downloaded the crown jewels of the
Directorate of Science and Technology
and sent it all to WikiLeaks in 2017.
Google Vault 7.
Vault 7 documents, Vault 7 revelations,
it will knock your socks off.
Um thousands and thousands of pages. It
makes what Chelsea Manning leaked
look like, you know,
scroll from a sixth grader.
So, he revealed that
the CIA has developed technologies to,
for example, remotely take over your car
by hacking into the chip, right? Why
would the CIA want to take over your
car?
To make you drive off a bridge? Maybe?
To make you drive into a tree and kill
yourself?
To make you drive into an abutment
and make sure that there's no way you
can survive cuz they've got the thing
going 140 miles an hour and you can't
control it?
They develop technology to
to
reverse your smart TV
to make the speaker into a microphone
with the TV still appearing to be off
so you don't know that it's broadcasting
everything that's being said in your
house to CIA headquarters?
You know, they were able to
they were able to hack into other
countries um
most sensitive technological systems and
to leave little scraps of code but the
scraps of code are written in Russian or
in Persian
in Farsi.
So people say oh the [__] Russians
hacked into us or the Chinese or the
Iranians.
And actually no, it it was us.
But you'll never know it.
I mean there's almost too much in Vault
7 to even go into. It's incredible I'm
going to give a talk about it at a
hacker conference this coming weekend.
So um
you know, couple what the CIA was trying
to do in the 50s with MK Ultra and its
subcomponents compared to what it is
technologically able to do today
and it is terrifying.
Terrifying. Damn dude, yeah that is uh
that is gnarly.
Um
going back to the the psychologist
what
what kind of psychological pro okay, let
me let me frame it up before they ask
the question.
Let's say you recruit me as an asset. I
work in you know, the Iranian Embassy
somewhere and you meet me at a cocktail
party and I say oh John this this guy is
he's he's a wonderful guy. I'm going to
get to know him a little bit.
>> Yeah. And we become best friends as you
say over 6 9 months whatever the period
is.
>> Yep. And you pitch me one day. Uh-huh.
And
what I'm getting at is what is the
psychological process that an asset goes
through? Like what kind of crisis goes
on as this happens?
Yeah, that's a great question.
There's a There's a little dance that's
happening here.
I I asked one of my instructors when I
first went into the operational
training,
"What percentage of people that you have
pitched in your career said yes?" He
said 100.
100%. He said, "If you are not 100%
certain that this guy is going to say
yes, run for the hills.
Because he's going to out you, you're
going to get arrested, you're going to
get expelled from the country, he's
going to report you to his own
intelligence service, and then you're
not going to be able to travel to half
the countries in the world."
That happened to a colleague of mine
where
you know, we we all read each other's
cables, and we're like, "Dude, keep up
the good work, man. You're going to get
him. Next meeting you're going to get
him." Right? So, I'm reading my
colleague's cables, and it's It couldn't
be going any better. And
he asks headquarters permission. You
have to get permission to make the
actual pitch.
It's very paperwork heavy.
So, headquarters says,
"Go for it. Go with God." And he makes
the pitch, and the guy literally runs
screaming from the room.
And next thing you know, his ambassador
calls our ambassador, and his government
lodges a formal diplomatic complaint
with our government. What are you going
to do? You're going to say, "Yeah, my
guy's a an undercover CIA guy." So, you
can't say that.
So, you say, "No, no, no, no, no. This
is just a misunderstanding. It was a
language thing. Our guy doesn't really
speak your language very well, and your
guy doesn't speak English very well.
This was just an innocent
misunderstanding. But, we understand if
you're upset, so we're going to instruct
our guy not to ever talk to your guy
again."
And that's
uncomfortable.
Besides the fact that you look like an
idiot at headquarters because you've
been telling us for 9 months how well
things are going, and in fact the guy
never had any intention of allowing you
to recruit him.
Like, what have you been doing all this
time?
You're supposed to be wining him and
dining him and showing him the better
finer things in life so that he says,
"Hey, you know, I'm kind of liking I
make $500 a month. This guy's ordering
$200 bottles of wine, and he paid for us
to go on vacation, and he bought me a
Rolex.
I'm going to say yes to this."
And in fact, he says not just no, but oh
hell no.
So,
what you're looking for
is a vulnerability. This is This is a
very important word in the what's called
the the asset acquisition cycle. The
asset acquisition cycle is spot, assess,
develop, recruit.
I spot you at a diplomatic cocktail
party.
I assess that you have access to
information that I that I want.
I develop you by creating this
friendship.
And then, I recruit you.
Now, by the time I recruit you,
you know exactly what's going on. You're
not an idiot.
And why am I spending all this money on
you?
You know, where am I getting all this
money?
Rolexes and, you know, fancy vacations
and
What's up?
So, you're not an idiot. You know what's
happening here.
And so, you do it very gently.
And I say, "Dalton, listen. You know how
I feel about you. You're my best friend.
I love you. I love your wife. My wife
loves you. My wife loves your wife. Our
kids are friends.
We're going to be friends forever.
But,
I haven't been 100% honest with you.
And
I hope you're not going to be upset, but
I'm actually a CIA officer undercover."
That's called breaking cover.
And I I hope you're okay with that.
I know you're going to be okay with
that, cuz you know exactly where this is
going.
I've already identified your
vulnerability. Maybe your kid is sick
and needs medical treatment in the
United States. Maybe
your kid wants to go to school in the
United States. I can get your kid
accepted to literally any university in
America and I'll pay for it.
Any university in America.
100% paid. So long as you keep giving me
and my,
you know, colleagues who replace me and
replace each other what they ask for.
Um
So I take you off to the side and I say,
"Listen, just for your protection
we can't be seen as friends anymore. Our
relationship has to become clandestine
from this point on. And so we're going
to meet once a month
at a predetermined site at a
predetermined time and date
and then we'll carry on from there.
Now, if you're from an enemy country
I don't want you to defect. That's the
last thing I want because if you defect
your value ends today cuz you lose your
access. Well, I don't care what was
happening yesterday. I want to know what
your country's going to do tomorrow.
Right?
So the goal is
let's say you and I are stationed in uh
you know, Bogota.
I want you to go back to Iran
or Russia or China
or Cuba
and you're going to take with you
a bedroom
a bedroom set that I give you.
Right? And the dresser
is going to have a
a transmitting device embedded in the
back of it.
And so
you're going to type your reports onto a
chip.
You put the chip in the device, you hit
a button that's hidden in the back of
the drawer,
and it does a burst transmission that
lasts about a half of a second or a
tenth of a second, and it's going to
send your report back to CIA
headquarters. And because the burst only
lasts for a tenth of a second,
nobody's going to be able to intercept
it.
They're going to say, "Oh, there was
just a transmission. It lasted a tenth
of a second. We have no idea where it
came from."
Because once you get back to Iran or
Cuba Russia or China or whatever,
I want you to tell me what's going on
every single day in your office. And
then I want you to try to get a
promotion, and then get transferred to
the office of American Affairs.
And I want the names of everybody in
that office. I want to know the names of
their sources inside the United States,
so the FBI can start arresting them.
And then we take it from there.
And then I can pay you in any way you
want. You know, we can open an account
at the CIA Credit Union, which we're
very happy to do.
Or we can give it to you in gold or
diamonds or Bitcoin or you know, however
you want to handle it.
We'll give it to you.
How many of them Okay, so I'm just
thinking like an asset, they a lot of
them are probably very prideful, right?
I know a big a big vulnerability is I'm
the smartest guy in the room. I'm older
than them. I'm smarter than them. I'm
more experienced than them. I'm more
connected than them. So they fancy
themselves as smart people. Shrewd,
perceptive.
And yet they didn't see this coming. So
internalizing that,
how many of them want to know if it was
a setup from the start? And like do they
ask you for like a face-saving thing?
You know what I mean? None of them want
to know.
That that they were duped into this or
that they walked right into it. Right?
So what you do in every single meeting
is you tell them how important they are.
Your information is so important.
It's going directly to the President of
the United States. I made a I got to cry
once in a meeting.
So,
he gave me some information. It was
good. It was
the analysts were happy with it. It
helped fill in a couple of gaps.
He thought it was the greatest
information that's ever been passed to
the American government. So, I said,
"Listen." I go, "Buddy,
your information went directly to the
President of the United States." He
said, "You're kidding me."
I said, "No. Directly to the President."
I said, "I wrote the report. I sent it
to the White House. He looked at the
report." What did he say? I said, "The
President read the report and he said,
'You're kidding me.'" Oh, he goes like
this, "Oh my god."
So, I I write this up. I said, "Oh, I
told him it went to the President." My
boss says, "You want to have some fun?"
He goes, "Dummy up a uh
an award certificate. Put the CIA seal
on it."
So, I said, "Oh, that would be fun."
So, I did a I did a
in in just in Word, you know?
And clip art. So, I did this, you know,
Central Intelligence Agency, United
States of America. I had the guy's name,
uh certificate of whatever. You put the
CIA seal on it and then I just forged
the director's name cuz how's he going
to know what the director's signature
looks like?
So,
I go to the meeting the next month and I
said, "I told you last month
that your information went directly to
the President of the United States." And
he said, "Yes."
I said, "I have something for you from
the director
of the Central Intelligence Agency." And
I give him this phony certificate. He
looks at it and he bursts into tears.
And I said, "Congratulations, my
friend."
>> [laughter]
>> I said, "But listen, you know, I have to
take this back and keep it in the safe
because you can't be seen with this.
You'll be killed."
He goes, "Of course, of course. I can't
believe it. Oh my god, Aubrey.
I had him hooked.
He was ready to name his kids after me.
That's how successful it was.
But you just play on their egos and they
eat it up.
They eat it up cuz they're all
narcissists anyway. Not all, but you
know, most of them are narcissists. They
need to be stroked.
So after you after you assess what the
vulnerability is, right? You do like,
you know, actually let me let me ask
that first. Is
how much of how much of the work is done
on the front end by analysts and
targeting officers versus you in the
field asking discovery questions? None
of it.
None of it's done by them.
No.
None of it. Um I shouldn't say none. 99%
of it is is not done by them. When I was
an analyst,